A Guide to the Bailey-Craddock-Lawson Family Papers, 1837-1915
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Bailey-Craddock-Lawson Family Papers, 1837-1915
Library of Virginia
28301
29 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Charles O. Willis, Alexandria, Virginia, 29 April 1974.
Biographical/Historical Information
Yancey Bailey (1755-1804) married Sarah Fowlkes (d. 1833) in 1772 and had nine children, two of whom were John (1795-1871) and Harriet Catherine (1800-1873).
John Bailey married Elizabeth Scott (1797-1884) in 1816 and had two daughters, Frances Madison (1817-1900) and Jane (1819-1899). Frances Madison Bailey married Reuben Charles Traynham (1800-1870) in 1835 and had eight children including, Thomas Benjamin (1836-1910). Jane Bailey married David Lawson (1803-1877) in 1839 and had a daughter, Sallie Fannie (1845-1936). Thomas Benjamin Traynham and Sallie Fannie Lawson married in 1869 and had a son, David Lawson (1869-1930), among other children.
Harriet Catherine Bailey married Thomas Easley (1780-1835) in 1814 and had nine children: Sarah Ann (1815-1821), Robert (1819-1819), Thomas, Jr. (1823-1847), Mittie, Harriet Amanda (b. 1825), Fannie Yancey (1827-1885), Charles Bruce (1832-1889), William Henry (1833-1861), and Mary Bailey (1834-1928). Thomas Easley Jr. graduated from West Point in 1846 and was killed at the Battle of Churubusco in 1847 during the Mexican War. Harriet Amanda Easley married William Lee Owen. Fannie Yancey Easley married Dr. Charles James Fox Craddock (1819-1865) in 1852. William Henry Easley served as Captain of the Black Walnut Dragoons (Company C) of the 3rd Virginia Cavalry, C.S.A. and died of typhoid fever in 1861. Mary Bailey Easley married Dr. John Wimbish Craddock (1824-1884) in 1853.
John A. Wimbish (1756-1818) married Nancy Williams (d. 1836) and had three children: Eliza Jasper (1800-1867), Judith A., and Abraham Wimbish. Judith A. Wimbish married John B. Carrington. Eliza Jasper Wimbish married Dr. Granville Craddock (d. ca. 1829) in 1815 and had four children Sarah Cornelia Wimbish (d. 1881), Charles James Fox, John Wimbish, and Mary Louise Craddock. Sarah Cornelia Wimbish Craddock married 1) Edward Branch and 2) E.M. Jarvis. Dr. Charles James Fox Craddock married Fannie Yancey Easley. Dr. John W. Craddock married Mary Bailey Easley. After the death of her first husband, Eliza J. Wimbish Craddock married Dr. Abram M. Poindexter (1809-1872) and had two more children: Abram Wimbish (1840-1864) and Fannie (ca. 1838-1870). Abram Wimbish Poindexter was killed at the Battle of the Crater in 1864 during the Siege of Petersburg. Fannie Poindexter married Reverend James Taylor.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1837-1915, n.d., consisting primarily of letters discussing family news, but also the death of Lt. Thomas H. Easley at the Battle of Churubusco during the Mexican War (#5-6), Mexico City and the effects of disease on the occupying U.S. troops during the Mexican War (#7), the aftermath of the Battle of Big Bethel and the activities of Company C, 3rd Virginia Cavalry in late June 1861 (#12), the seige of Petersburg (#13), geographical descriptions of both Leipzeig and Sonnburg, Germany (#17), and genealogical information about the Trayhan family of Halifax County, Virginia (#23). The majority of the letters are transcribed in Betsy Lawson Willis and Martha Barksdale Craddock, comp., Sketches and Genealogy of the Bailey-Craddock-Lawson Families of Virginia and North Carolina... (Alexandria, Virginia: 1974).
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- E[liza] J. Poindexter, Poplar Avenue, to Mrs. Edward M. [Sarah] Branch, New Orleans, 28 November 1837, 3 p., ALS with additional leaf.; For a typescript of this letter see Betsy Lawson Willis and Martin Barksdale Craddock, comp., Sketches and Genealogy of the Bailey-Craddock-Lawson Families... (Alexandria, Virginia: 1974), p. 149-150; hereafter cited as Willis and Craddock.
- Judith A. Carrington, Halifax C. H., to Mrs. Sarah W. Branch, New Orleans, 30 December 1837, 3 p., ALS with additional leaf.; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 150-151.
- R[ebecca] F. W[imbish], Poplar Avenue, to [Mrs. Sarah Wimbish Branch], 30 September 1838, 4 p., ALS (mutilated).; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 153.
- Eliza J. Poindexter, Poplar Avenue, to Mrs. Sarah W. Jarvis, Houston, Texas, 12 May 1844, 4 p., ALS with additional leaf.; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 156-157.
- D[avid] R[umple] Jones, Adjutant, 2nd Infantry, City of Mexico, to F. Y. Easley, 31 October 1847, 2 p., ALS; Announcing the death of T. H. Easley in the Battle of Churubusco. For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 44.
- George E. Pickett, Mexico, to Mr. W[illia]m L. Owen,1 December 1847, 4 p., ALS; Regarding T. H. Easley's life and death, condolences, personal comments and reminiscences. Added on to Pickett's letter is a letter from D. R. Jones to [William L. Owen], 8 December 1847, regarding transportation of T. H. Easley's remains and personal effects. Negative photostats of this item were previously accessioned as 27891. For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 45-46.
- E. M. Jarvis, Mexico, to Sarah W. Jarvis, Barksdale, Virginia, 13 January 1848, 4 p., ALS; Regarding description of Mexico City and the effects of disease among the American troops. For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 158-159.
- W. H. Easley, Hillsboro, to [Fannie Yancey Easley], 1 October 1848, 3 p., ALS; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 49-50.
- Fannie [Yancy] E[asley], Charleston, South Carolina, to [Mrs. Harriet C. Easley], 3 July 1850, 4 p., ALS; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 50-51
- Assignment by the executors of the estate of Thomas Easley to his heirs, 9 January 1854; Memorandum of Agreement on the rights of William H. Easley and Mary B. [Easley] Craddock to their inheritance, 9 January 1854; Receipts of William H. Easley, 11 January 1854, and John W. Craddock, 31 January 1854, for their portions of the estate, 3 p., ADS
- John Wimbish, Steamboat Astoria, Mississippi River, to Mrs. Sarah W. Branch, Houston, Texas, 12 November 1838, 3 p., ALS; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 154-155.
- W. H. Easley, Bethel Church, to Dr. John W. Craddock, Black Walnut, Halifax County, Virginia, 16 June 1861, 4 p., ALS with envelope; Describing the aftermath of the Battle of Big Bethel. For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 55.
- [Capt. Abram Wimbish Poindexter], Petersburg, Virginia, to [Rev. and Mrs. Abram and Fannie Poindexter, Halifax County, Virginia], 9 July 1864, 4 p., ALS; Discusses refugees and the conditions and events in the army. For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 161.
- [Mrs. Fannie Poindexter Taylor], Culpeper Court House, to [Mrs. Sarah Wimbish Jarvis, Black Walnut, Virginia], 26 December 1865, 2 p., ALS; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 160.
- A. M. Poindexter, Richmond, Virginia, to John [Wimbish Craddock], 27 May 1870, 4 p., ALS; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 162-163.
- R. L. Traynham, Roanoke, Virginia, to Mr. D. L. Traynham, Halifax County, Virginia, 17 December 1884, 2 p., ALS with envelope
- J. M. Mercer, Sonneburg, Thuringia, Germany, to Mrs. [___] Craddock, 24 January 1886, 3 p., ALS
- Sallie F. [Traynham], Harmony, Virginia, to Mr. David L. Traynham, Hyco, Halifax County. Virginia, 7 October 1886, 4 p., ALS with envelope and two enclosures; Enclosures - two gummed decorative labels on display cards.
- Ruby Traynham, Harmony, Virginia, to Mr. D. L. Traynham, Hyco, Virginia, 27 November 1886 and 3 February 1887, Two letters, 2 p. each, ALS with envelopes
- Jannie [___], Danville, Virginia, to Mr. D. L. Traynham, South Boston, Virginia, 27 January 1888, 2 p., ALS with envelope
- Lily C. Cabaniss, Reidsville, North Carolina, to Mrs., J. E. Ragland, Hyco, Halifax County, Virginia, 30 August 1888, 6 p., ALS with envelope
- "Cousin Jannie", Danville, Virginia, to Mr. D. L. Traynham, South Boston, Virginia, 16 December 1888, 4 p., ALS with envelope
- James H. Traynham, Laurens, South Carolina, to Mr. Thomas Traynham, Harmony, Virginia, 11 January 1889, 2 p., ALS with enclosure; Enclosure - business card of Traynham and Dial, Wholesale and Retail Dealers.
- J. R. Guthrie, Clover Depot, to Mr. David L. Traynham, South Boston, Virginia, 7 June 1893, 2 p., ALS with 1 p. printed for filled out by hand; With enclosure receipt for taxes on land of Mrs. Rebecca Traynham, Halifax County, Virginia.
- Mamie [___], Gibson's Station, North Carolina, to David [___], 9 June 1893, 5 p., ALS
- Warner Moore and Co., The Dunlop Mills, Richmond, Virginia, to R. W. Lawson and Co., South Boston, Virginia, 31 May 1894, 1 p., TLS
- J. Bailey Owen, Henderson, North Carolina, to Mrs. Mary B. Craddock, Cluster Springs, Virginia, 6 July 1915, 1 p., TLS; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 48.
- [___], to Dr. Craddock, n.d., 1 p., AL
- F[annie] Y. Craddock, to (Mary Bailey Easley Craddock?), n.d., 2 p., ALS; For a typescript of this letter see Willis and Craddock, p. 165.